<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<metadata
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dc:title>Li et al (2008) GPlates Reconstruction</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Zheng-Xiang Li</dc:creator>
<dc:subject>empty</dc:subject>
<dc:description>Rodinia (from 'rodit', meaning 'to beget' or 'to give birth' in Russian) was a 
supercontinent that existed during the Neoproterozoic and was named as it was thought to have 
been the original supercontinent that present day continents formed from (McMenamin and McMenamin, 
1990). Its amalgamation began just after 1100 Ma, with the collision of Baltica (north-east Europe) 
and Amazonia (north-east South America) along the east coast of Laurentia (North America), 
Australia-Antarctica, the Kalahari (South Africa) and the Congo (Central Africa) cratons colliding 
along the west, south-west and south margins respectively and Siberia (eastern Russia) colliding 
with the northern margin. Due to its central position in the supercontinent, Laurentia is considered 
the heart of Rodinia, and its breakup, occurring around 750 Ma, resulted in all of these continents 
rifting off it and reforming into Gondwana (from 650-520 Ma, including South America, Africa, 
Australia, India and Antarctica) or Laurussia (North America and Baltica).

A number of reconstructions have been proposed over the past twenty years for modelling the breakup 
of Rodinia, and they all differ slightly in the exact timing and orientation of the continents. The 
model depicted here is from Li et al. (2008), a large, international collaborative project that was 
a contribution to IGCP 440, and is probably the most comprehensive review of global evidence for 
Rodinia. The model is based on a number of lines of evidence, including palaeomagnetism, regional 
geology, palaeobiology and plate kinematics.
</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>empty</dc:publisher>
<dc:contributor>Zheng-Xiang Li</dc:contributor>
<dc:date>empty</dc:date>
<dc:type>empty</dc:type>
<dc:format>GPlates-compatible file formats</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>DOI:10.1016/j.precamres.2007.04.021</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Li, Z.X., Bogdanova, S.V., Collins, A.S., Davidson, A., De Waele, B., Ernst, R.E., 
Fitzsimons, I.C.W., Fuck, R.A., Gladkochub, D.P., Jacobs, J., Karlstrom, K.E., Lu, S., Natapov, L.M., 
Pease, V., Pisarevsky, S.A., Thrane, K., Vernikovsky, V., 2008. Assembly, configuration, and 
break-up history of Rodinia: a synthesis. Precambrian Research 160, 179.210.</dc:source>
<dc:language>empty</dc:language>
<dc:relation>empty</dc:relation>
<dc:coverage>Global | 530-1100 Ma</dc:coverage>
<dc:rights>empty</dc:rights>

</metadata>