<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<metadata
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dc:title>Wright et al (2013) GPlates Reconstruction</dc:title>
<dc:creator>Nicky Wright</dc:creator>
<dc:subject>empty</dc:subject>
<dc:description>We base our Phanerozoic relative plate motions on the rotation model made 
available in the Supplement of Golonka (2007), and use block outlines based on terrane boundaries 
used in Seton et al. (2012) and interpretations of magnetic and gravity anomalies. The relative plate 
motions in this model are similar to those in Scotese (2004). Paleozoic plate motions are based on 
continental paleomagnetic data due to the absence of preserved seafloor spreading histories. Although 
paleomagnetic data on continents do not provide paleolongitudes, the relative plate motions and 
tectonic unity of two continental blocks can be inferred from commonalities in the apparent-polar 
wander (APW) paths (Van der Voo, 1990). If two or more continents share a similar APW path for a 
time period, then it can be inferred that these continents were joined for these times. In the ideal 
world such APW paths would coincide perfectly, but due to the inherent uncertainties and errors in 
paleomagnetic measurements, we assume that the clustering of paleopoles indicates a common tectonic 
history between two or more plates during Paleozoic times. Similarly, tectonic affinities can be 
deduced from the continuity of orogenic belts, sedimentary basins, volcanic provinces, biofacies 
and other large-scale features across presently isolated continents (Wegener, 1915). We assign 
absolute plate motions to Africa, as the base of our rotation hierarchy, for the Phanerozoic based 
on the smoothed APW spline path from Torsvik and Van der Voo (2002). All continents that moved 
independently in the absolute reference frame (i.e. relative to the spin axis) from the Golonka 
(2007) model were recalculated as equivalent relative rotations to a conjugate neighbouring plate, 
connected hierarchically in our plate circuit.
</dc:description>
<dc:publisher>empty</dc:publisher>
<dc:contributor>Nicky Wright</dc:contributor>
<dc:date>empty</dc:date>
<dc:type>empty</dc:type>
<dc:format>GPlates-compatible file formats</dc:format>
<dc:identifier>doi:10.5194/bg-10-1529-2013</dc:identifier>
<dc:source>Wright, N., Zahirovic, S., Mü R. D., and Seton, M. Towards community-driven paleogeographic 
reconstructions: integrating open-access paleogeographic and paleobiology data with plate tectonics, 
Biogeosciences, 10, 1529-1541</dc:source>
<dc:language>empty</dc:language>
<dc:relation>empty</dc:relation>
<dc:coverage>Global | 0-540 Ma</dc:coverage>
<dc:rights>empty</dc:rights>

</metadata>